（長十郎）大変だ。
どうかされましたか？
This is serious!
Is something wrong?
島まで　あとどのくらいですか？
How much longer before
we reach the island?
There's been no wind, so...
風がありませんからね。
でも　大丈夫です。
But we'll be okay.
土影の使者様との
合流時間までには。
We're supposed to rendezvous with
the Tsuchikage's messenger by...
それでは遅い。
え？　長十郎さん。
That's going to be too late!
What? Chojuro?
先に行きます！
I'm going on ahead!
君たちも　なるべく急いで！
Please follow
as soon as you can!
（ガイ）う～っ　まいった…。
まだ地面が揺れている…。
I give up!
The ground is still shaky...
（アオバ）結局　最後まで　ガイさんの
船酔いは治りそうもありませんね。
You were seasick until
the very end, weren't you, Guy?
最後？
（ヤマト）ここでの補給を終えれば→
The end?
After we replenish supplies here,
あとは雷の国まで一直線ですから。
we will head straight to
the Land of Lightning.
ハァ…　そうか。
I see.
まぁ　いろいろあったが
無事　任務達成できそうだな。
A lot of things happened,
but it looks like
we'll accomplish our mission.
ところで　ナルトは？
By the way, where's Naruto?
（ナルト）プハ－ッ！
みそとんこつもいいけど→
Miso and pork broth is good,
but seafood broth's great too!
海鮮ってのもありだな　こりゃ。
まったく。　止める間もなく
飛び出していくんだから。
Damn it. He dashes out
before you can stop him.
まぁ　どうせ　ここに１泊するんだ。
小さな島だし　問題ないさ。
We'll be staying here
for a night.
And it's a small island.
There's no harm in that.
うぉ　まだ揺れる…。
ガイさん…。
Whoa... It's still shaky.
Guy...
（赤ツチ）へぇ　この島から先が
水の国ってわけか。
From here on out,
it's the Land of Water, huh.
（黒ツチ）つ～か　ちっこい島だな。
Still, what a tiny island.
こら。　あんまり動き回ると
迎えの人が困るだに。
Hey, we should stop
moving around so much
or the people we're supposed to meet
won't be able to find us.
いいじゃねえか。
早く着きすぎたんだろ。
So what?
We arrived early, didn't we?
今のうちに
そのへん見て回ろうぜ。
– We should look around while we can.
– Guy! Are you all right?
ガイさん　大丈夫ですか？
（ヤマト）なかなか回復しませんね。
– It's taking a while to get over it, isn't it?
– I can't do that.
そもそも土影様は
わいに使者を任せたんだに。
Lord Tsuchikage appointed me
as his messenger.
勝手についてきて。
かたいこと言うなよ　赤ツチ。
You just decided to
come along all on your own.
Don't quibble, Akatsuchi.
水の国は
今まで外交を持たなかった国だ。
The Land of Water hasn't had
diplomatic ties with anyone.
データをとるチャンスなんか
なかったんだから。
So we've never had
a chance to gather intel.
まっ　手を組んだところで
お互い　忍同士さ。
We may have teamed up now,
but we're still shinobi.
状況次第で　どう転ぶか。
Who knows when
the situation will change?
（巌流）お前らが土影の使者か？
Are you the messengers
from the Tsuchikage?
なんだ　お前？
Who are you?
命を…　もらう！
I'll be taking...
your lives!
来るだに！
Follow me!
ちょっ！　あたいらが
同盟国の忍だと知ってのことか？
Hey, do you know
that we belong...
to the Allied Shinobi Force?!
（キリ）うるさい！　死ね　岩隠れ！
Shut up and die, Stone ninja!
Who are you?!
いったい何者だに！？
それは！
That's—!
グァッ！
赤ツチ！　クッ！
Akatsuchi!
うぅっ…。
おい　なんで岩と霧が
やりあってんだ！
Hey! Why are the Stone and
Mist fighting here?
んなもん　こっちが聞きてえよ！
いきなり襲ってきやがった！
That's what I want to ask!
They just attacked us
out of the blue!
どけ　木ノ葉。
Move it, Leaf!
そういうわけには　いかねえだろ！
You know I can't do that!
邪魔だ！
You're in the way!
あれ？
What?
Even if you are from the Leaf,
if you interfere...
邪魔立てするなら
木ノ葉といえども！
Please stop!
（長十郎）やめてください！
（黒ツチ）新手？
Is that backup?
止めるな　長十郎。
Don't stop me, Chojuro.
No. This violates
Lady Mizukage's will.
いいえ。　このようなことは
水影様の意思に反します。
命令により　あなたを
止めさせていただきます！
Per her orders...
I'll have to make you stop!
《できることなら…》
That's if I can...
あれ？　消えた。
What? He disappeared.
あの～　皆さん　ご無事ですか？
I-Is everyone all right?
はぁ？　ご無事なわけねえだろ！
What?! How can
we be all right?
ちょ…　怖い。
So scary...
なんで　あたいらが
お前らに襲われんだ？　あ！？
Why would you
guys attack us? Huh?
おい！
もめてる場合じゃねえってばよ。
Hey!
This is no time to be arguing!
いけない！
おい　運ぶぞ。
This isn't good!
Hey, let's take him.
木ノ葉の下っ端。　お前も手伝え。
え？
Hey, Leaf underling! Help us!
俺　下っ端？
Me? An underling?
ibitsu na merodll de dekita aisareru beki ikimono da
Made from a distorted melody,
I'm a creature that should be loved
seika wa agerarenakute mo kokoro ga utatte iru kara
Even if I can't better myself,
I'll continue to sing from my heart
dore dake tsuyoi ame koete aisareru beki ikimono ka?
What storms must I overcome
To be a creature who should be loved?
yakusoku ga mamorenakute mo kokoro wa utatte iru kedo
Even if you can't keep your promise
My heart will keep on singing, but...
dono doa nokku shite aketara ii?
Which door should I knock on and open?
aketara doko e mukattara ii?
Once I open it, where should I go?
hitori ja kaerenai kara
I can't go home by myself
dareka o matte ita dake
I was just waiting for someone
kimi ga ima ichiban aitai hito wa dare?
Who is the one you want to meet the most?
kokoro no naka de dake hanaseru hito no kazu wa fuete iku
The number of people that I can only speak to in my heart
keep increasing
dakara tsuyoku naritakatta tada
So I just wanted to be strong
bokura mada yomitarinai monogatari
Our story just hasn't been told enough
muriyari owarenai koto wakattete
We know it's not something we can just quit
dare mo mina jibun no mama
Because we all want to be ourselves
tsuyoku naritakatta kara
We wanted to be strong
Naruto's Vow
な　なにぃ！？
W-What?!
医者がいねえって
どういうことだよ！
What do you mean,
"there's no doctor"?
申し訳ありません。
ここは辺境の島ですから。
I'm very sorry,
this is an isolated island...
でも
こちらに向かっている僕の隊に→
But there's a Medical Ninja
in my team
医療忍者がいます。
間もなく到着予定で…。
that's headed this way.
They will be arriving shortly.
おい　タオル持ってきたぞ。
Hey, I brought some towels.
報告してねえで汗を拭いてやれ。
気が利かない下っ端だな。
I don't need a report.
Just wipe his sweat.
You're not very thoughtful
are you, underling?
てか　誰が下っ端だ　おい！
Who're you calling "underling"?!
こんなとこ　うろついてんのは
伝令役の下忍に決まってる。
Who else but
a lowly messenger genin
would be hanging around
a place like this?
いいから　やれ。
Hurry up and get to work.
なんで俺が…。
Why me?
クソッ！　なんで　こんなことになる。
Damn it!
Why'd it turn out like this?
やつらは　いったい…。
Who are they anyway?
先ほど
水影様より伝令がありました。
I just received a message
from Lady Mizukage.
里から　数名の忍たちが
一斉に姿を消したと。
Several shinobi have suddenly
dropped out of sight from the village.
彼らは　今回の同盟に
反対していた者たちで→
They oppose
the current shinobi alliance
その中心にいるのが上忍の巌流。
and the central figure among them
is a jonin named Ganryu.
（黒ツチ）赤ツチをやったやつか。
Is that the one
who injured Akatsuchi?
はい。　彼は→
Yes.
He is the sole survivor
of an incident
ヨスガ峠の悲劇と呼ばれる事件の
生き残りです。
known as
the Tragedy of Yosuga Pass.
ヨスガ峠？
Yosuga Pass?
我々　霧隠れと岩隠れが→
You're probably aware of
the deep-seated hostility
長く憎み合っていたのは
ご存じだと思いますが→
between the Mist and the Stone.
その発端となった事件のひとつ
といわれています。
That incident is said to
have started the hostility.
十数年前
各地の術を集めていた雲隠れが→
About ten years ago,
the Hidden Cloud went around
collecting jutsu from
each of the Nations.
我々の里の機密書類を
強奪したことがありました。
They seized a highly confidential
document from us.
当日　同盟を結んでいた
岩隠れとともに→
On that day,
in a team led by Ganryu,
巌流率いる部隊が
書類の奪還に赴いたのです。
the Hidden Stone, along
with our allies the Mist,
set out to recover the document.
気をつけろよ。
雲のやつらがいるのは　この先だ。
Stay alert.
The Cloud are just up ahead.
（スイレン）大丈夫。
この先は　岩のサポートがあるもの。
No need to worry.
We have our allies from
the Stone beyond this point.
それはそうだが…。
That may be so, but...
この任務が成功したら→
If this mission is a success,
岩と霧の同盟が強固だってことを
諸国に示せるわ。
we will show
the rest of the lands
that there is solidarity
between the Stone and Mist.
そうしたら
少しだけ平和に近づける。
That way, we can get
a little bit closer to peace.
スイレン…。
Suiren...
思うの…。　いつか
そんなふうになればいいって。
That's what I wish. I hope it could
be like that some day.
な…　なぜだ！？　お前たちは
我々と同盟を結んでいるはず！
W-Why?
We are supposed to be allies!
渡せ！　その文書を持ち帰ることが
我々の任務だ。
Hand it over.
Our mission is to return home
with that document.
許さない…　絶対に！
This is absolutely...
unforgivable!
フフフフ…　やれ！
Kill him.
スイレン…。
Suiren?
見たかったな…　平和。
I wish I could have seen...
peace.
スイレン…　ジュンサイ…　クッ！
Suiren... Junsai...
うわぁ～っ！！
少しだけ平和に近づける　か…。
"That way, we can get
a little bit closer to peace," huh.
巌流さん。
Ganryu...
あの人は岩隠れを憎み続けている。
だからこそ　今回の同盟は→
He continues to hate
the Hidden Stone.
Perhaps that is why
it was difficult for him
彼にとって許しがたいもの
だったのかもしれません。
to accept this new alliance.
まさか　あたいらを襲ったのは…。
Don't tell me
that's why he attacked us.
彼は　あなた方　岩隠れの使者を
暗殺することで→
I believe he intends
to get his revenge
by assassinating you,
the messengers of the Stone,
かつての復讐を果たすとともに→
望まぬ同盟を壊そうと
しているのではないでしょうか？
and by destroying the alliance
which he opposes.
そんな　くだらねえことに
つきあわされてたまるか！
As if we'd stand by and
allow such a thing to happen?!
あの…　どこに？
Uh, where are you going?
やられる前に　こっちから出向く！
I'll get him before he gets me.
待ってください！
この件は　我々が…。
Please wait!
We will settle this matter—!
うっ！
うぅっ！
おい！
Hey!
お前らは　赤ツチを見てろ。
You guys take care
of Akatsuchi.
((忍の世界は
憎しみに支配されている。
The world of the ninja
is ruled by hatred.
答えが見つからんかったときは→
And if I can't find the answer,
(その答えを
お前に託すとしようかのぉ))
perhaps I will entrust you
to find it.
何のつもりだ？　下っ端。
What's the big idea, underling?
お前が　仲間をやられて
怒ってるのはわかる。
I understand you're angry
because your friend was hurt.
でも　行くのはやめろってばよ。
But don't go.
黙って
やられるのを待てってのか？
So I should wait quietly
until he comes for me?
そうじゃねえ。　でも　行けば
どっちかが死ぬことになる。
That's not what I mean!
If you go, one of you will die.
死ぬのは　あっちだ。
And it'll be him.
そういうことじゃねえ。
That's not it.
お前らをやりあわせるわけには…
いかねえんだ！
I can't allow you two...
– to fight!
わかんねえこと言いやがって。
What the hell
are you talking about?
止められるもんなら…
止めてみな！
If you think you can stop me,
just try!
Damn it!
There's no end to this!
ああもう　キリがねえ！
行かせねえってばよ！
We're not going to let you go!
このぉ！
Why you—!
またか…。
Not again!
お前を通すわけにはいかねえんだ。
We won't let you pass.
下っ端のくせに→
For an underling,
you sure have a nasty jutsu
for stalling people.
めんどくせえ足止め術
持ってやがるな。
話は　俺がつける。
だから　仲間の所に戻ってくれ。
I'll go and settle this.
So go back and
stay with your friend.
嫌だね。
あんま　あたいを見くびんなよ。
I don't want to.
Don't underestimate me.
急がねえと！
I have to hurry!
使者の１人が長十郎と離れ
こちらに向かっている。
One of the messengers
got away from Chojuro
and is headed this way?
ヘヘッ　好都合だな。
Perfect.
迎え撃ちましょう　巌流さん！
This calls for an ambush, Ganryu!
いや　俺だけで十分だ。
No. You guys stay out of this.
お前らは　もう里に帰れ。
You can return to the village.
いきなり何を言うんです！？
What are you saying?!
そうだ！
俺は親父を岩隠れに殺されてる！
He's right! The Hidden Stone
killed my father!
やるなら　俺も！
そうですよ！
I want to be a part of this!
– Me too!
– He's right, Ganryu!
残された者たちのことを考えろ。
Think about those you left behind.
お前たちの怒りと苦しみ。
Your anger and your hatred...
その思い　すべて俺が持っていく。
I will take every shred
of those feelings with me!
But...!
しかし…。
なぜ邪魔をする？
Why do you interfere?
I'm Naruto Uzumaki
of the Hidden Leaf.
俺は　木ノ葉の　うずまきナルトだ。
九尾の人柱力か。
The Nine Tails' Jinchuriki?
おっちゃんの事情は聞いた。
I heard your story.
But I came to stop you.
そのうえで　俺は
おっちゃんを止めにきた。
俺の師匠は　ペインに殺された。
My Master was killed by Pain.
だから
おっちゃんの悔しさはわかる。
So I understand
the bitterness you feel.
でも　こんなこと
やめろってばよ！
But you have to stop this!
お前は　ペインを殺し
復讐を果たしたと聞いた。
I heard you killed Pain
and got your revenge.
You're wrong.
違う。　あいつは
自分の力を使い切っただけだ。
He just used up all of his power.
復讐を望まなかったと？
そんなわけねえ。
Are you telling me
you didn't want revenge?
Of course not.
あいつを前にしたとき
憎くて憎くて　たまらなかった。
When he stood before me,
I was consumed with hate.
殺したくて　体中が震えた。
I wanted to kill him so much
that my entire body shook!
But I realized that wasn't enough.
でも　それだけじゃダメだって
わかったんだ。
Why not?
なぜ？
憎しみの連鎖が始まるからだ。
Because that just starts
a cycle of hatred.
一度始まりゃ
復讐が復讐を呼んで→
Once it begins, the cycle will
keep going for both sides.
Revenge begets revenge.
大事なやつが
どんどん死んじまう。
And people dear to us will die,
one after the other.
なるほどな。
I see. But I'm fully aware
of that already.
だが　そんなことは百も承知だ。
だったら　なんで！？
Then why?!
この道しかない。
あいつの願いに近づくためには。
There's no other path to take...
in order to make
her wish come true.
どういうことだってばよ。
What are you talking about?
このタイミングで復讐劇が起きたら→
If an incident of revenge
occurs here
the Five Kage will be forced
to think seriously...
火影たちは
真剣に考えざるをえないだろう。
about the difficulty and risk
involved in maintaining an alliance.
この同盟を組むことの
難しさと危うさ…。
そして　平和について。
And they'll also be forced
to think about peace.
平和？
Peace?
A village looks out for
its own interests.
里とは
己の利のために動くものだ。
そして　里同士の同盟など→
Villages form alliances,
but easily go back on them
to suit their needs.
それぞれの利害によって
簡単に覆る。
その中で　忍たちは
里の利のため裏切りを繰り返し→
For the sake of their villages,
shinobi have committed betrayals,
and fought and killed one another
time and time again.
対立し　殺し合ってきた。
五大国に　この忍の世に→
How many shinobi
do you think exist
within each of
the Five Great Nations,
他国の忍に対し　復讐心を持つ者が
どれほどいると思う？
who harbor hatred towards
shinobi from different lands?
今回動いたのは俺だが
こんなことは何度でも起きる。
This time, I started it.
But this kind of occurrence
happens all the time.
And not everyone can suppress
their desire for revenge like you.
そして　誰もが　お前のように→
復讐を
踏みとどまれるわけではない。
An alliance formed only
by the higher ranks
このまま
上辺だけの同盟を組んでも→
will just end up repeating the past.
同じことを繰り返すだけだ。
そんなこと…　ねえ。
That's not true.
Because I'll change the future!
そんな未来は　俺が変えてみせる！
どうして言い切れる？
How can you be so sure?
My master and my fellow shinobi
have entrusted me
俺は　師匠と兄弟子に託されてる。
to find the answer to
deal with hatred.
憎しみをなんとかする答えを。
The answer to
stop this cycle of revenge.
復讐の連鎖を止める答えを。
The answer to foster
understanding between shinobi!
忍同士がわかりあえる
その答えを。
They put their faith in me,
and I'm going to find the answer!
２人が信じてくれたから
俺は必ず見つけてみせる！
So have some faith
in me too, old man!
だから　おっちゃんも信じてくれ。
Even it happens gradually,
俺は少しずつでも→
平和ってやつに近づいてみせる！
I'll get closer to this thing
called peace!
And we will be just
a little bit closer to peace.
((少しだけ平和に近づける))
《スイレン…》
Suiren...
I found you, Ganryu!
見つけたぞ！　巌流！
You...
お前…。
Are you crazy?!
Jumping in front of him like that!
バカか　てめえ！
とんでもねえとこに
飛び込んできやがって！
Don't worry.
This is nothing.
心配すんな…。
たいしたことじゃねえよ。
Are you kidding me?
I used full force just now!
んなわきゃねえだろ！
思いきり斬ったぞ！
I can't afford... to die here.
俺は…　こんなところで
くたばってる場合じゃねえんだ。
I have too much to do still...
たくさん…　やることが…。
ちょ…　死んだら　あたいの責任か
国際問題か！？
Hey, is it going to be
my fault if you die?!
Is this going to become
an international incident?!
You must be kidding me!
冗談じゃねえ！　死ぬな～！
Don't die!
I'm not. I'm just resting
because it hurts.
いや…　痛いから
休んでるだけだから。
うずまきナルト…。
Naruto Uzumaki...
I understand.
わかった。　お前に託してみよう。
I'll put my trust in you.
Stop right there!
（長十郎）そこまでです！
I'm taking you into custody.
あなたを拘束します！
If you resist...!
おとなしく従わない場合は…。
I have no intention of resisting.
逆らう気はない。
それと　あいつの治療を頼む。
Also please tend to his wounds.
おい　霧の！　赤ツチは！？
Hey, you from the Mist!
What happened to Akatsuchi?!
I left a Medical Ninja to treat him.
医療忍者を残してきました。
His injuries are
not life-threatening.
命に別状はないそうです。
I see.
そうか…。
Ganryu...
巌流さん　これを。
Here.
The messenger you injured
entrusted this to me.
あなたが斬った使者の方に
託されました。
これは！
This is...
He returned the personal effects of
those who died at Yosuga Pass.
ヨスガ峠で亡くなった方の遺品の返却
及び→
Along with a formal apology
for that incident.
あの事件の正式な謝罪…。
That was the true purpose
of the messengers
それこそが　今回　土影様が→
dispatched by Lord Tsuchikage.
我が里に使者をたてられた
理由だそうです。
The Hidden Stone...
岩隠れが…　あの事件の謝罪を！？
apologized for that incident?
He did?
That stubborn old man?
あの頑固じじいが？
This was in order to strengthen
the new alliance
我ら　霧隠れとの同盟を
今度こそ強固なものにするために。
between the Mist and Stone.
そうか…。
I see.
あのおっちゃん
どうなるんだってばよ…。
What's going to happen
to that guy?
He will either be
executed or released.
（長十郎）死罪か追放か…。
これだけのことをしたんです。
He committed a serious crime.
I'm sure he is prepared
to face the consequences.
あの人も
覚悟してのことでしょう。
I don't think it will come to that.
（赤ツチ）きっと　そんなことには
ならないだに。
I got hurt because I made
a wrong turn and stumbled.
わいがケガしたのは
ちょっと間違って転んだからだに。
Right, Kurotsuchi?
なっ？　黒ツチ。
それ　昔の事件の
痛み分けのつもりか？
Are you saying this makes up
for that incident in the past?
ヘヘ…　霧に貸しを作っておく。
それだけのことだに。
I'm just going to have the Mist
owe us one. That's all.
ったく…　じじいだけじゃなく→
Maybe the old man wasn't
the only one
お前まで風影に
感化されたんじゃねえだろうな？
who had a change of heart
because of the Kazekage.
Kazekage?
風影…。
Hey, you Mist!
Remember, you owe us one!
おい　霧の！
あくまで貸しだからな！
Oh, yes. Thank you very much!
あっ　はい！
ありがとうございます！
And you, Leaf underling!
それと！　木ノ葉の下っ端！
Hey, your wound is still...
君　まだケガが…。
Sorry, but I left
my comrades waiting.
悪いけど
仲間待たせてんだ。　またな。
See you!
The least he could've done
was introduce himself!
名前くらい言ってけっての。
Hey, what happened to you anyway?!
（ヤマト）ちょっと！
どうしたんだい！？　その格好！
Well, how should I put it?
イヤッハハ…。　なんつうか
ちょっと間違って転んじゃって。
I made a wrong turn
and stumbled.
Stumbled? Where?
う～ん　転んだ…。　どこで？
Aoba! Is that all
you're going to say?
アオバさん！
突っ込むところ　そこですか！？
Never mind already.
んなことよりさ
明日は早えんだろ？
We have
an early start tomorrow, right?
So let's get everything ready,
and then hit the sack.
出発に備えて
さっさと休もうぜ。
Well, we had a change of plans.
いや　それがな　雷の船が直接
我々を迎えに来てくれるとの→
We got word that the ship
from the Land of Lightning
is coming to pick us up directly.
連絡が入った。
え？
そろそろ着く頃だな。
It should be here soon.
Oh, there it comes!
おぉ！　来た来た！
That's...!
あれが…。
fight!!
furishiboru dake sa saigo no itteki mo
I'm going to squeeze it down to the last drop
muda ni dekinaikara now is the time to go
Because I can't waste any of it, Now is the time to go
ikudo tsuma tsukimi to egaita yume wa
The dream that I created many times with you
ima koe kuma atte munune o sasu
I can now put it to words and it pierces my heart
it's not crazy
fight and fight, try and try for you
forever
kimi wa hitori janai
You are not alone
namida koete
Get over the tears
kimi to susunde ikou
I'll keep moving forward with you
nani mo kowaku narute na ii na
I'm not afraid of anything
this is the place to try
soshite bokura kitto tsunaida te o
I'm sure we'll never let go
kesshite hanasanaide asu e kakeru
Of each other's hands as we head for tomorrow
let's sing loudly
we are the one for the future
Next Episode
It's here! That must be the octopus coming to guide me.
All right!
Will we clash or be a smash?
If I dare say, it will be a no-go, whee!
I'm a brat-hating outlaw!
Who's this old man with the weird rhymes?
Next time on Naruto Shippuden: "Land Ahoy! Is this the Island of Paradise?"
Land Ahoy! Is this the Island of Paradise?
This old man's the Eight Tails' Jinchuriki?